A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller, Vice Presidential records xFA250
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Working Papers of the Vice President, 1974-1977; 18; 19.5 Cubic Feet 63 Volumes
  - Press Book (VII), April 12 - June 30, 1976 (Volume 56)
    Remarks, President Ford Committee Reception - Urban Club, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, April 12, 1976. Speech, Club of Rome Banquet, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, April 12, 1976. Press Conference, Des Moines, Iowa, April 14, 1976. Press Conference, Atlanta, Georgia, April 18, 1976. Speech, GOP Fund Raising Reception, Atlanta, Georgia, April 15, 1976. Transcript, WHO-TV appearance - Des Moines, Iowa, April 15, 1976. "60 Minutes" interview, April 18, 1976. Remarks, President's Commission on Personnel Interchange Dinner, April 20, 1976. Telegram exchange with Senator Jackson, April 22, 1976. Speech, Annual Neptune Award Dinner, Washington, DC, April 28, 1976. Statement, Proposals for a National Health Policy, Washington, DC, April 29, 1976. Remarks, George Washington Inaugural Ceremony, Washington Monument, April 30, 1976. Transcript, "Issues and Answers," May 2, 1976. Press Conference, San Francisco, California, May 4, 1976. Speech, Commonwealth Club of California Luncheon - San Francisco, California, May 4, 1976. Press Conference, Los Angeles, California, May 5, 1976. Speech, Los Angeles World Affairs Council Luncheon, May 5, 1976. Speech, Queens County Annual Republican Dinner, Astoria, NY, May 7, 1976. Speech, International Press Institute, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, May 10, 1976. Interview with Ard (German Television Network), May 10, 1976. Remarks upon arrival at Udine, Italy, May 13, 1976. Remarks upon departure from Udine, Italy, May 13, 1976. Remarks upon arrival at Berlin, Germany, May 13, 1976. Speech, U.S. Mission Headquarters, Berlin, Germany, May 14, 1976. Speech, Schloss Charlottenburg Luncheon, Berlin, May 14, 1976. Remarks upon departure from Berlin, Germany, May 14, 1976. Remarks upon arrival at Frankfurt, Germany, May 14, 1976. Speech, Frankfurt City Hall, Germany May 14, 1976. Statement, Opening of Glass Exhibition, Frankfurt, Germany, May 15, 1976. Remarks, Frankfurt, Germany, May 15, 1976. Remarks upon departure from Frankfurt, Germany, May 15, 1976. Remarks between the President, Vice President, and Daniel Parker, aide, May 17, 1976. Speech, Bicentennial Ceremony, Yorktown, Virginia, May 19, 1976. Remarks, Hamilton County President Ford Committee Dinner, Cincinnati, Ohio, May 20, 1976. Speech, Fifteenth Anniversary Synagogue Council of America, Newport, Rhode Island, May 23, 1976. Speech, National Conference on Regulatory Reform, May 26, 1976. Transcript, "Face the Nation," May 30, 1976. Speech, USAF Commencement, Colorado Springs, Colorado, June 2, 1976. Press Conference, USAF Academy, Colorado Springs, June 2, 1976. Remarks on Ronald Reagan, June 3, 1976. Speech, Maryland State Republican Convention Dinner, Ocean City, Maryland, June 4, 1976. Press Conference, June 4, 1976. Speech, National Broadcast Editorial Association Annual Meeting, June 9, 1976. Remarks, Dedication of Old Senate Chamber, June 16, 1976. Speech, National Housing Conference Dinner, June 16, 1976. Remarks, NYS Republican Committee Meeting, NYC, June 17, 1976. Speech, NYS Republican State Dinner, NYC, June 17, 1976. Press Conference, Greensboro, North Carolina, June 18, 1976. Speech, North Carolina Republican State Dinner, Greensboro, June 18, 1976. Remarks, GOP Reception, Greensboro, June 18, 1976. Press Conference, West Orange, New Jersey, June 21, 1976. Remarks, NJ Republican Pre-Convention Dinner, West Orange, New Jersey, June 21, 1976. Speech, American Friends of Hebrew University Luncheon, Washington, DC, June 22, 1976. Press Conference, Hauppauge, NY, June 24, 1976. Speech, Nassau County Republican Committee Dinner, Hauppauge, NY, June 24, 1976. Remarks, Congressman Paul Findley Award Luncheon, June 30, 1976.
  - Press Book (VIII), July - September 22, 1976 (Volume 57)
    Remarks, Chartbook Ceremony - Census Bureau, July 1, 1976. Speech, Pageant of Freedom, Washington Monument, July 4, 1976. Toast to Queen Elizabeth, July 8, 1976. Speech, Inaugural Ceremony Albert Einstein Spacearium, July 15, 1976. Press Conference, Wilmington, Delaware, July 19, 1976. Speech, 1976 Victory Kick-off Dinner, Claymont, Delaware, July 19, 1976. Speech, Republican National Hispanic Assembly Reception, Washington, DC, July 29, 1976. Press Conference, Bar Harbor, Maine, August 2, 1976. Press Conference, Seal Harbor, Maine, August 2, 1976. Luncheon Toast to President Kekkonen of Finland, Washington, DC, August 4, 1976. Dinner Toast to President Kekkonen of Finland, Washington, DC, August 5, 1976. Speech, Republican Platform Committee, Kansas City, August 9, 1976. Remarks, Republican National Convention Committee on Resolutions, Kansas City, August 9, 1976. Press Conference, Kansas City, August 12, 1976. Transcript, "Meet the Press," August 15, 1976. Speech, Republican National Convention, August 16, 1976. Speech, Republican National Convention, August 19, 1976. Q&A, White House lawn, September 14, 1976. Speech, Local Republican Reception, Buffalo, NY, September 15, 1976. Remarks, Coffee Rally, Buffalo, NY, September 16, 1976. Press Conference with Senator Dole, Buffalo, NY, September 16, 1976. Remarks, United Airlines Terminal, Rochester, NY, September 16, 1976. Press Conference with Senator Dole, Rochester, NY, September 16, 1976. Remarks, Hancock International Airport, Syracuse, NY, September 16,1976. Press Conference with Senator Dole, Syracuse, NY, September 16, 1976. Remarks, Broome County Airport, Binghamton, NY, September 16, 1976. Press Conference with Senator Dole, Binghamton, NY, September 16, 1976. Press Conference with Senator Dole, NYC, September 16, 1976. Remarks, President Ford Headquarters, New York City, September 16, 1976. Press Conference, Chicago, Illinois, September 21, 1976. Transcript, TV appearance, Chicago, Illinois, September 21, 1976. Speech, Jim Thompson for Governor Dinner, Chicago, Illinois, September 21, 1976. Press Release, re: Campaigning in Cleveland, Columbus, & Cincinnati, Ohio September 22, 1976. Press Conference, Cleveland, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Remarks, Opening of Ford Headquarters, Cleveland, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Speech, Cuyahoga County Republican Breakfast, Cleveland, Ohio, September 22, 1976.
  - Press Book (IX), September 22 - October 4, 1976 (Volume 58)
    Transcript, TV appearance Channel 5, Cleveland, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Speech, Columbus Bar Association Luncheon, Columbus, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Press Conference, Columbus, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Transcript, TV appearance, Columbus, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Press Conference, Cincinnati, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Transcript, TV appearance Channel 12, Cincinnati, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Transcript, TV appearance, Cincinnati, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Speech, Hamilton County Republican Rally, Cincinnati, Ohio, September 22, 1976. Remarks, Candidate's Brunch, Hasbrook, New Jersey, September 28, 1976. Press Conference, Dover, New Jersey, September 28, 1976. Speech, Morris County Republican Fund Raiser Luncheon, Dover, New Jersey, September 28, 1976. Press Conference, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, September 28, 1976. Transcript, KYW, "Mike Douglas Show," Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, September 28, 1976. Interview with WCAU TV, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, September 28, 1976. Speech, Salute to Distinguished Republicans Dinner, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, September 28, 1976. Press Conference, Erie, Pennsylvania, September 29, 1976. Transcript, TV appearance WICU-TV, Erie, Pennsylvania, September 29, 1976. Speech, GOP Dinner Support Committee, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, September 29, 1976. Press Conference, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, September 29, 1976. Remarks, Ribbon Cutting Ceremony President Ford Committee, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, September 29, 1976. McPherson Interview, London England, October 4, 1976. BBC Interview, London, England, October 5, 1976. Press Conference, U.S. Embassy, London, England, October 4, 1976. Speech, Opening of North American Indian Art Exhibit, London, England, October 4, 1976.
  - Press Book (X), October 7-19, 1976 (Volume 59)
    Chronological collection of statements, speeches, press releases and press conference transcripts
    Press Conference, O'Hare Airport, Chicago, Illinois, October 7, 1976. Press Conference, Hilton Hotel, Chicago, Illinois, October 7, 1976. Remarks, Hilton Hotel, Chicago, Illinois, October 7, 1976. Speech, Salute to the President Dinner, Chicago, Illinois, October 7, 1976. Speech, Columbus Citizens Committee Dinner, New York, October 9, 1976. Remarks, New York County Republican Committee Supporter Dinner, New York, October 9, 1976. Speech, Ukrainian-American Congress Committee Annual Dinner, New York, October 9, 1976. Introduction of President, Salute to President Ford Dinner, New York, October 12, 1976. Transcript, KOG-TV appearance on "Jim Dunbar Show," San Francisco, California, October 13, 1976. Press Conference, San Francisco, California, October 13, 1976. Transcript, KCRA-TV appearance, Sacramento, California, October 13, 1976. Press Conference, Portland, Oregon, October 13, 1976. Transcript, KOIN-TV Interview with Ted Bryant, Portland, Oregon, October 13, 1976. Transcript, KGW-TV appearance, Portland, Oregon, October 13, 1976. Remarks, Reception, Portland, Oregon, October 13, 1976. Remarks, VIP Reception, Portland, Oregon, October 13, 1976. Speech, John Spellman Volunteer Breakfast, Seattle, Washington, October 14, 1976. Transcript, Seattle Today Show, Seattle, Washington, October 14, 1976. Press Conference, Seattle, Washington, October 14, 1976. Remarks, Kent County Airport, Grand Rapids, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Speech, Hal Sawyer Luncheon, Grand Rapids, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Speech, Lunch with Rocky, Grand Rapids, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Remarks, Kalamazoo Municipal Airport, Kalamazoo, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Remarks, United Airlines Room, Saginaw, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Speech, Fund Raiser Reception, Saginaw, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Remarks, Ponchartrain Hotel, Detroit, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Transcript, WWJ-TV Channel 4 appearance, Detroit, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Speech, COBO Hall, Detroit, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Speech, Michigan State Republican Committee Dinner, Detroit, Michigan, October 18, 1976. Remarks, Candidate Reception, Bloomington, Minnesota, October 19, 1976. Remarks, Elephant Club, Minneapolis, Minnesota, October 19, 1976. Speech, Elephant Club Luncheon, Minneapolis, Minnesota, October 19, 1976. Remarks, Candidate Rally, Normandale Community College, Bloomington, Minnesota, October 19, 1976.
  - Press Book (XI), October 20, 1976 - January 18, 1977 (Volume 60)
    Speech, Joan Braden's Consumer Conference, Washington, DC, October 20, 1976. Q&A, Consumer Conference, Washington, DC, October 20, 1976. Speech, National Press Club, "One Week to Go," Washington, DC, October 26, 1976. Remarks, Senior Citizens Rally, Franklin Square, NY, October 27, 1976. Press Conference, Senior Citizens Rally, Franklin Square, NY, October 27, 1976. Remarks, Women's Tea Rally, Franklin Square, NY, October 27, 1976. Remarks, Reception, Student Complex, Hofstra University, Hempstead, NY, October 27, 1976. Speech, Business, Labor, Education Community Leader Dinner, Hempstead, NY, October 27, 1976. Remarks, Island Park Republican Rally, Island Park, NY, October 27, 1976. Letter to President-Elect Carter, November 3, 1976. Remarks between President and NAR, the Cabinet Room, November 5, 1976. Eulogy for Gus Levy, November 7, 1976. Interview, "US News and World Report," November 9, 1976. Speech, Williamsburg Foundation Dinner, Williamsburg, Vir.ginia, November 12, 1976. Speech, Conference on Future of Productivity, Washington, DC, November 16, 1976. Speech, Republican Eagles Luncheon, Washington, DC, November 16, 1976. Speech, 10 Outstanding Young American Women, Washington, DC, November 16, 1976. Statement, Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services, Washington, DC, November 16, 1976. Remarks, History of Kykuit, Pocantico Hills, November 17, 1976. Speech, 22nd Annual Session of the North Atlantic Treaty, Williamsburg, Virginia, November 18, 1976. Remarks, Ceremony designating John Davison Rockefeller Estate as a National Landmark, Pocantico Hills, November 21, 1976. Speech, 50th Anniversary Celebration of China Institute, NYC, November 30, 1976. Speech, 100th Anniversary of Pakistan's Founder Jinnah, Washington, DC, December 2, 1976. Speech, Georgetown University Graduate Student Forum, Washington, DC, December 8, 1976. Remarks between NAR and Texas Governor John Connally, Washington, DC, December 9, 1976. Speech, Political Science Association, Mount Vernon College, Washington, DC, December 14, 1976. Telegram to Mrs. Daley on the Death of Mayor Daley, December 21, 1976. Remarks, President's Awards for Distinguished Federal Civil Service, Washington, DC, January 12, 1977. Address to the Senate, Washington, DC, January 18, 1977.
  - Letters of Appreciation (I) (Volume 61)
    Correspondence received by NAR in recognition of his service as Vice President of the United States. Alexandrakis, Menelas - Marsh, John O.
  - Letters of Appreciation (II) (Volume 62)
    Correspondence received by NAR in recognition of his service as Vice President of the United States. Marshall, Anthony D. - Zehudi, Ruleshi
  - Index (Volume 63)
- Foreign Affairs and National Security, 1974-1977; 19; 18.6 Cubic Feet 17 record cartons 4 document boxes
  Biographical/Historical note
  Nelson A. Rockefeller served as the second unelected Vice President in the history of the United States. (President Gerald Ford, whom Rockefeller served as Vice President, had been the first unelected Vice President.) Although Mr. Rockefeller acted relatively extensively in the areas of foreign relations and national security, his main focus, in the view of many observers, was on domestic policy. At the same time, the work that commanded the greatest public attention during the Ford-Rockefeller Administration was that of the CIA Commission. The recommendations issued by the commission strongly affected the policy and operation of the CIA for a generation.
  Jonathan T. Howe graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy in 1957 and earned a Ph.D. from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University in 1969. His early career in the Navy was spent on submarines. Prior to serving with Vice President Rockefeller, he was on the National Security Council staff as military assistant to the Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, 1969 to 1974. Later appointments included senior military assistant to the Deputy Secretary of Defense, 1981 to 1982; Assistant to the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 1987 to 1989; and Deputy Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, 1991 to 1993. He also served in Somalia as the Special Representative of the UN Secretary-General, 1993 to 1994, and after retirement from the Navy, he ran a philanthropic foundation.
  Arrangement
  The arrangement of the series, while mainly by broad topic, is inconsistent on occasion. However, the folder order has been kept intact to maintain a direct correlation to the separated, classified pages. For this same reason, there are no Folders 122 to 192.
  RESTRICTIONS
  Several files and individual pages in this series are closed. See the folder list for details. In accordance with Archive Center policy, correspondence with or substantively about living members of the Rockefeller family is closed. The exception is reference to Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller in her official capacity as wife of the Vice President. Additionally, material bearing a U.S. government security classification is closed.
  This series contains documents that were declassified by the U.S. government during a review by government officials at the Archive Center from 2003 to 2006. Any document that remains classified since the review has been removed from its folder and replaced with a separation sheet to note its original and current locations. Therefore, all materials in the open folders is now declassified, whether or not the classification stamps on them indicate otherwise. Almost all of the declassified documents prominently display a federal agency's declassification stamp and date.
  The original title of this series was Foreign Policy and Travel. It was changed during the archival processing to Foreign Affairs and National Security to more accurately reflect the contents of the folders. However, the original title may appear on separation sheets and other processing-related documents.
  The bulk of this series of papers consists of files kept by Captain Jonathan T. Howe, Assistant to the Vice President for National Security Affairs, who served Nelson A. Rockefeller during his entire vice presidency (December 19, 1974 to January 20, 1977) in the Gerald R. Ford Administration. The contents reflect international relations and national security topics that Capt. Howe monitored closely for the Vice President. He also oversaw Mr. Rockefeller's appointment schedule on these matters and coordinated with Peter Wallison, Counsel to the Vice President, on suggested responses to inquiries involving foreign officials or national security issues.
  The topics covered include International Travel, National Security, Meetings with Foreign Dignitaries, Meetings with U.S. Officials, the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy (Murphy Commission), Intelligence, Countries/Regions, and the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States (alternately Rockefeller or CIA Commission). Additionally, there are several folders of background information on the Operations Coordinating Board, which originate from Mr. Rockefeller's tenure as Special Assistant to President Eisenhower during the mid-1950s. Also significant in this series are monthly folders of Captain Howe's chron file. (See topic descriptions below.)
  Noticeably absent is documentation of direct communication between the Vice President and President Ford on any of these matters. However, there are numerous memos throughout the series from Secretary of State Henry Kissinger--particularly under International Travel--and National Security Affairs Assistant Brent Scowcroft--particularly under National Security Council Meetings.
  Additionally, some folder numbers use a decimal extension (for example, Folder 13.1, Folder 336.4). This designation can mean that either it is a folder created to subdivide an overfilled original folder or it is a closed folder of restricted documents. The latter are prominently labeled as such in the folder list.
  DESCRIPTION
  International Travel (Folders 1-57) ranges from the Vice President serving as the official U.S. representative at funerals of foreign dignitaries or national celebrations to meetings with heads of state or their top ministers. In 1976 he attended several international celebrations to commemorate the U.S. Bicentennial. Some personal travel files exist as well. Every trip includes a substantial amount of U.S. State Department cables, itineraries, background information on the countries being visited, cultural protocol tips, and follow-up correspondence.
  National Security folders are scattered throughout the series but include titles such as National Security Council Meetings, Defense Department Briefings, Cruise Missiles, and Pertinent National Security Developments. Intelligence-related folders also crop up sporadically; Intelligence Review and Reorganization, President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (PFIAB), and Terrorism are a few title examples.
  Meetings with Foreign Dignitaries (Folders 64-88) include arrangements, agenda, and either notes or verbatim accounts of the discussions. They are arranged by mouth in roughly reverse chronological order. Meetings with U.S. Officials (Folders 93-97) have similar contents but are less numerous. They too are arranged in roughly reverse chronological order. See the Materials of Special Significance section for specific names and dates of significant meetings with those officials.
  In January 1975, President Ford recommended that Vice President Rockefeller fill an open seat on the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy, more commonly referred to as the Murphy Commission. The commission was established by an act of Congress in June 1972, and it concluded its work in June 1975. Capt. Howe often sat in for the Vice President at the commission meetings. Folders 103-121 hold correspondence, agenda, report drafts, press clippings, and meeting minutes. Folder 120 contains a thorough summary of the history of the commission, including a candid memo on its workings and aftermath written by Capt. Howe to Mr. Rockefeller in January 1977.
  Additionally, the contents of more than 30 binders of working papers and background information on the Murphy Commission are at the end of this series in Folders 393-429. Items labeled Books directly correlate to commission meetings during the Vice President's tenure. A tab-level listing of their contents is provided. Items labeled Background Workbooks are background materials from meetings in 1973 and 1974, prior to Mr. Rockefeller's membership on the commission. There is no tab-level listing for them, but the folders are grouped by topic (e.g., intelligence, internationals economics). Lastly, the eight-volume set of the published final report of the Murphy Commission (1 report volume and 7 appendices) has been removed from this series and added to the RAC library collection (library catalog #353.001 COM).
  Folders 232-284 cover issues on specific countries/regions, from Angola to Yugoslavia. These files may contain duplicates of documents found under International Travel but often have unique ones. They are arranged in semi-alphabetical order by country name.
  Captain Jon Howe's Chron Files (Folders 314-320.5 and 333-344) are an informative source on both the daily activities of the Office of the Vice President and the significant national and international events during those years. They are arranged by month in approximate reverse chronological order. A few reference files are interspersed among them.
  In December 1974 at President Ford's request, Nelson Rockefeller became chair of the newly appointed Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States, which was established by Executive Order as a result of ongoing claims of abuse of jurisdiction against the federal agency. The commission, which came to be known as both the Rockefeller Commission and the CIA Commission, is documented from its inception to its final report in Folders 322-332.2 and 346-392. Also among these files are Cold War-era materials from the Operations Coordinating Board that contain information on studies on psychological warfare, Soviet military capabilities, and the Quantico Panel from 1953 to 1955. They are all contemporaneous with Mr. Rockefeller's service in President Eisenhower's Administration as Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
  MATERIALS OF SPECIAL SIGNIFICANCE
  Numerous folders in this series contain materials of special significance for research on Nelson Rockefeller as Vice President, on national intelligence, and on international affairs during the mid-1970s.